<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ankur Goel]]></title>
  <link href="http://AnkurGel.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://AnkurGel.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-24T16:07:27+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://AnkurGel.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ankur Goel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[StatSample]]></title>
    <link href="http://AnkurGel.github.io/blog/2013/04/24/statsample/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-24T13:51:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://AnkurGel.github.io/blog/2013/04/24/statsample</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/sciruby/statsample">Statsample</a> is a statistical library for Ruby and is actively developed by folks at SciRuby. Currently, Statsample is supported with Ruby 1.8.7, 1.9.1, 1.9.2 and ruby-head.</p>

<p>Statsample is currently makes use of Ruby/GSL which uses NArray for vector and matrix operations. It conflicts with the SciRuby&#8217;s NMatrix which also uses the same class names - NMatrix and NVector. Thus, this conflict makes Statsample unusable for system which already has NMatrix. To aid this, SciRuby developed a fork of <a href="http://github.com/SciRuby/rb-gsl">rb-gsl</a> which makes use of NMatrix instead of NArray. I went through it&#8217;s code structure and found it to be great. Devs did a great job in removing many references of NArray and made use of NMatrix in lieu of that.</p>

<p>Statsample is <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/sciruby/wiki/Google-Summer-of-Code-2013-Ideas#statsample">purposed idea</a> for <a href="http://google-melange.com">Google Summer of Code 2013</a> program. And, I am excited about making Statsample more flexible by covering various aspects:</p>

<ul>
<li>Make Statsample compatible for Ruby 1.9.3+</li>
<li>Enable Statsample to require <a href="http://github.com/SciRuby/rb-gsl">rb-gsl fork</a> instead.</li>
<li>Add more tests to the code and cover the documentation using existing style of NMatrix.</li>
<li>Implement modules for Generalized Linear Models(GLM) and Time Series Analysis.</li>
</ul>


<p>I have been playing around with existing codebase by writing few examples and test cases from few days and had <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!topic/sciruby-dev/SqXJLJnd6Xs">discussion</a> about this with fellow folks at SciRuby (John Woods, Claudio Bustos and Carlos Agarie). I&#8217;m very grateful for their response and persuasion. The discussion with them helped me to clarify many aspects which were a little obscure earlier. :)</p>

<p>Just before writing down this blog-entry, I was trying out <strong>TimeSeries</strong> class and it&#8217;s methods. I simply loved it - the ease with which I was able to compute the operations, I learnt back in Digital Signal processing such as lagging of series, autocorrelation, exponential moving average etc is <em>mindblowing</em>. It currently supports many basic operations, which after the successful execution of this project can definitely be expanded.</p>

<p>I will be delighted to work on Statsample in this summer, if given an opportunity.</p>

<p>Cheers! <br/>
- Ankur Goel</p>

<p><em>PS</em>: I will try to blog with example codes in next posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
